[Laughter]
[Music]
okay I'm here with my good friend
Stephen Lewis
Stephen Lewis likes to think about
things in fact I don't know another guy
who thinks so much about so many things
almost no a couple people in the world
who I really think and you're one of
them so I kind of landed on a Jewish
interpretation of Christianity I think
one of the reasons was a Jewish
interpretation of Rene Girard that is
and one of the reasons was I was
fascinated I was obsessed with
anti-semitism and trying to resolve that
problem in the context of Christianity
and so I was kind of working on that in
my head for a long time and it seems to
me that Rene Girard developed a theory
which which completely reconciled
Christianity and Judaism this was kind
of my Jewish moment even though it was
from reading a Christian thinker and the
Jewish moment is the what Rene Girard
claims to be the absolute he Rene Girard
claims that he articulated the absolute
which is a very strong statement then
you knew he was making a very strong
statement huh and the way he he he
states that in his writing is is done in
a very tricky way he he comes out and
this big blasting surprised to say yes
guess what this is it's the absolute
this is actually what it is and and the
absolute is one simple phrase it's the
defense of the innocent victim that's
what the absolute is and he it there's a
long theory there's a in elaborate
theory he develops before he leads the
the the reader to that moment and it's a
theory that he developed for I think in
the 1960s he said it took him a long
time to proper figure out how he was
gonna how he was going to articulate it
he took it took years to figure out how
he was gonna say it but he understood
the theory
a long time before so was 1970s that he
broke that theory in the early seventies
and for me it was a very big deal I mean
from to me it's probably it he may be
the most important Hurst Perry it's it's
such because he also he identifies so
many things he identifies at least he
claims to and the what he thinks is the
is the foundation of human culture and
it more or less it's the moment a
recurring moment that happened millions
and millions of times and it in way back
in prehistory mostly but also continuing
into history and progressively
diminishing where we slowly created a
social construct which separated us from
our animal origins from our it it
created a created a social super
imposition upon our biological beings
and it was a very very dark thing what
happened but nonetheless it is the raw
material with which we construct society
and culture today tonight can I stop you
for a second because I just had a
thought
is that the story of Cain and Abel right
which is the story of the first people
yeah it's totally related to Cain and
Abel it's more it's closer to Abraham
the story of Abraham and Isaac then the
story of Cain and what is very-- it's
all related like the Bible the Judaism
is totally obsessed with this and it's
obsessed with this dark this very this
thing that this this dark feature of of
the human experience which which we
absolutely have to control we have to we
we can't let it control us we have to we
have to rein it in and and contain it
and if we don't it controls us and this
controlling force is a recurring for
Rene Girard as a recurring force of
collective murder record a recurring
pattern of collective murder
mostly featured in deep prehistory
progressively diminishing as history
advances so there's a a slow process of
becoming aware of this and he says the
Bible is what Bibles does this better
than any other cultural focus so so
that's the story of human sacrifice and
correct which means which means a bunch
of people gathering around the weakest
most innocent person and making them
redundant blaming them for for whatever
happened or because they're weak or and
can't keep the tribe going or first of
all human sacrifice is a big fat lie the
word the whole term human sacrifice is a
is a term that's used it's an older term
and it it refers to a it represents
something that is not understood but it
where is the observation that a human is
being killed by by a group and so and
and and then there's since it's often
coded in in elements of religiosity
therefore it's called human sacrifice
Rene Girard points out that this is
actually a deeply entrenched cultural
mechanism of a culture lying to itself
about what's actually happening so
there's this he he basically says that
culture is founded on a the dark
recurring moment of cultural murder in
collective murder in which we lie about
what happened so here's here's basically
he says that we we are very imitative
animals we we engage in where we're
completely pretty supposed to imitate
each other but this is many ways totally
irrational in some way it's kind of a
synonym of desire and in a sense as a
result it's an illusion of desire at the
same time it's just simply imitating
another is is what he seems to be saying
desire is i I don't like the way he I
think I have a problem with with his
definition of desire but nonetheless see
he's talking about this great force of
imitation and what happens is one
imitates another and then another
imitates and then what you have is this
this whole group imitating the same
pattern of behavior
there tends to be a rivalry with it
that's probably what why the term desire
matters for sure are because what
happens is one tries to outdo the other
in him in imitating the exact same
pattern of imitative behavior and what
you have is this snowballing effect of
collective imitation and what the
problem the problem with that is it's
totally irrational for one and it's
resolving nothing and it's it's
escalating into pandemonium's because
there's this intense rivalry about you
know about something which is totally
irrational and all it is is a a an
imitative pattern of behavior and what
happened and it's something that seems
it's spontaneously happened and doesn't
you know how Wow and why this this
worked is utterly mysterious but
basically in that great snowballing of
mimetic desire there would be a sense
that things were about to erupt into
uncontrolled mass violence and someone
in the group and this would be a
relatively small tribal group all the
same someone in the group would
spontaneously say it's his fault or turn
fault and it was usually someone who was
anyone able to follow the imitative
patterns didn't have the capacity was
either mentally delayed or or physically
deformed or in some way didn't have the
capacity to to follow these patterns of
imitation and because they weren't
following it then they were the eyeballs
out of the of the whole snowballing
process that person was spontaneously
accused of being the one who caused this
entire pandemonium and the the group the
collective group would in turn all
spontaneously in the same wave of
imitative fervor
would agree absolutely everybody in the
group would be wrapped up in this
imitative pattern except those who did
spontaneously agree to choose a
representative scapegoat correct and it
was taught it was basically totally
irrational and then they would in turn
so that was they the accusation first
came and then the the agreement the unit
the unit the the unanimous agreement
from the entire group was the trial
basically and and so the the verdict was
a medias and and everybody agreed in
other words there was a judge and that
was the accuser and then there was a
jury who all immediately immediately
agreed and I'm only saying this Roni
we're only superimposing a much later a
form of Justice which is the court of
law on this is a ancient prehistory and
and then they would in turn kill the
person they will get just a question how
is that different from how animals
behave like an animal you know animals
animals no animal animal might might get
rid of the weakest person right or you
know because the weakest person might be
a drain on the resources of the I don't
like get rid of the weakest now I don't
know if that's the case that I think you
always are unique and practicing this
within this particular practice I don't
think it's a unique are they unique in
their scale or are they actually unique
and you know that's a good question I
mean the question but I have heard that
humans are unique in this I don't you
know whether other animals practice
bizarre things where members are the
members of the the group they kill a
single member of the group gets killed
by by the entire group I don't know if
that's I think what's unique about
humans is they represent they use they
have representative they have adults
they make representations
that's what okay that's what you think
about our brain and for your answer well
I I haven't got that
so that's the first so that I haven't
gotten to that part I'm getting there so
again that's that's the first prime so
the so the group the tribe the group has
just killed someone killed a scapegoat
and what happens in that moment is the
whole group comes down and so the and
and how and why this this calming occurs
because someone was just killed by the
is utterly strange and mysterious but
nonetheless this is what happened it
happened over and over and over and over
again and so the the act of killing
someone accused of the the uncontrolled
mimetic patterns was was a a deep
unconscious mechanism which succeeded in
in calming down the entire tribe they
would they would all stop and and and
and for a time the rivalry and the the
mimetic snowballing had would disappear
completely and and so a temporary peace
would would reign over the group and
this discovery became what it became
something that was worshipped what they
Girard theorizes that what they what
they did was they would credit they
would they began to deify
the person who was just killed because
the person had brought peace to the to
the tribe and so in other words it was
meant to be and and so what they
actually what in turn actually happened
was they would then in turn worship the
person who had just killed as a God
because that person would what had
brought peace upon the the tribe and
they would do this for a time they would
they would continue to they would do
this for a time until until the until
the that particular God had faded from
memory essentially which you know what
might happen
I don't mean you can imagine I can only
imagine how long that would be and this
however this cycle of mementos ISM would
return and and at another snowballing
and it would usually involve a different
pattern of behavior
you know the last time there were who
knows maybe they were talking they were
they were discussing rocks and so they
would they would the next thing to be
having a fight about rocks and and then
it would escalate into this grand tribal
crazy pandemonium about rocks and then
they killed someone and then they would
de fi the person killed the person
killed de if in turn deified would
somehow would be associated with the
fight over rocks that they had just had
and the next time will be about trees or
next time it would be about sky next
time it will be about clothes or beauty
or all consec sounds like the beginning
of some kind of narrative of the of the
tribe right well basically the filling
in of every shade of meaning involved a
tremendous snowballing tremendous
internal mimetic struggle which was
resolved by killing someone in turn
worshiped and then what would happen was
a piece invested a mental sense of a
false sense of peace invested in the
whatever they were fighting about
whether it was a key or a thumb so you
know thumbs who's got the biggest thumb
or whatever and and each and every time
that happened it would add and the
worshipping of the of the the killed
person would invest language into the
meta sized piece of Metis ISM is
Gerard's term which means increasingly
uncontrolled imitative behavior which
snowballs and spins out of control
that's what he means when the Metis ISM
and and so basically this was a
extremely long process with which he
speculates may have been hundreds of
thousand years where each and every
shade of nuance of meaning will actually
and and and and the worshipping of the
person killed involved a an investment
of language would it would involve a
repeating a deification of of a given
piece of language would would emerge out
of that
defying the the peace invested the sense
of false peace derived from that
repeated experience of killing someone I
don't know if you're getting wits it
means that so you have to you have an
innocent victim that then you and the
whole tribe is brought into this frenzy
and they kill the innocent victim and
then there's a period a period of
appeasement because they've they've made
the sacrifice which lasts for a certain
time until the tension builds up again
and again and and there's some other
issue and then and then they find
another victim and each time they're
there creating the story of themselves
in the sentences okay you're getting
you're getting most of it but what I'm
trying to get at here is the creation of
language yeah the story with each with
each it seems to me that they may be
maybe the persons killed had names or
something or a but they there would be
an audience you know going way back in
time it might be and so at first the
person killed will be no but then later
they were they they began to distinguish
from it and then they were Bertha and
each person killed would have a
distinguishing sound and over time these
these this would develop they would
bring together different sounds and then
it would become big and bad and bored
and rock and rock and skis sky and so
associated with whatever they were
imitating whatever they were fighting
about
so whatever they were pointing to and
competing over would then be invested in
in a in a certain sound which he
eventually became the syllabic sub
structure of our language basically I
think Gerard Lee thinks that which is a
damn radical bloody theory it's a major
major gotten up there and so each part
of our language is as a result I'm not
sure if I'm getting it some of his
escape he thinks our linguistic
substructure substrata is basically
composed as a bait ISM is a deep muddy
compost of murders
uh-huh each and every one of them and
and and we started to create compound we
became creative with it once once the
compost was there we could do stuff with
it and and and and that became you know
that we started to develop other ways of
doing things but basically there's a
there's a little and the thing about it
they would kill someone and then they
would de Fi that person saying this was
meant to be and they would dare fire the
person killed but it was all a big fat
lie all it was was a murderous just a
murder and it did and it happened to
resolve it happened to calm people down
and so in other words our syllabic
substructure the substrata of human
language and this is every tribe without
exception says Gerard all around the
world the the substrata of human
language is based on is based on one
Nagas after another of human hypocrisy
basically each and every each and every
syllable is born from a hypocritical
moment in which the whole tribe killed
someone and then lied to themselves
about what really happened very dark
theory yeah that's dark for sure
what he also says and in other words
there's a there's a deep sense of blame
an extremely profound sense of blame
rooted in our but it's also a
concealment of there's also an illusion
of peace or something like that and and
not only that this this affects our
sense of other tribes of other cultures
because we had this immediate sense of
we we don't see it in ourselves what we
see to them that they they're a bunch of
violent savages we can see we sense the
we sense the the hypocrisy in their
language and stuff but we don't see it
in ourselves we see it in them it's
easier to see the other side it's easier
to see the apocrypha right the way you
don't see your own back yeah yeah yeah
and and so basically I think this theory
it just explains everything now Gerard
is a Christian he's believes in God and
and and the reason he is this and he
he's also claims that the Jewish Bible
it's a full account although in a
disparate form its spread out in in bits
and pieces in different parts of the
Bible you have to piece it together
yourself just to show how the Jewish
Bible explains it actually has a full
explanation for this he says the
Christian Testament has a more
concentrated more explicit in your face
totally in your face explanation
especially in the Gospels of of this
particular occurrence okay and it's
already there and Cain and Abel and
Abraham and Joel come into fruition
until I mean it's most obvious the most
obvious sacrifices is of Jesus right
that's its most obviously in the Jewish
Testament in the Book of Isaiah and he
gives about 10 or 20 citations to the
first looked at in Isaiah it's actually
quite shocked it's quite amazing what
what I said what's it says in Isaiah
about about the killing of innocents and
how they're used escape boats and it's
all this comes tough his point is this
is deeply unconscious
that's Gerard's point it is so
unconscious that it is even though it
isn't expressed in a totally explicit
form he see he illustrates that it is it
is very explicit
it's very explicitly stated in the
Gospels it has only been transformed
into a rational theory in the 20th
century
he says he's he he's the second the very
first it's confessing he says the very
first was Nietzsche but Nietzsche didn't
didn't even it seems like he didn't even
know he did it or something anybody
Nietzsche based there's a there's a he
identifies a an aphorism in the world of
power where he says this is in in in his
one of his last books it might be his
last book actually it's called I see
Satan fall like lightning to rené girard
slash book was written and it was
published in 2000 he says he identifies
this Nietzsche and aphorism where
Nietzsche says it all boils down to this
this is what it all boils down to do we
sacrifice it or don't we and Nietzsche's
answer was yes we do sacrifice it so
Gerard
I thought this was a very important
effort Mbeki theorized that nietzsche
basically got sick
shortly after this and basically lost
his mind
and he felt that nietzsche gave the
wrong answer even though he identified
to say it all it just to say it all
boils down to this do we or don't we
sacrifice that means he had made the
discovery he was the first recording boy
Nietzsche's whole philosophy is based on
amor fati right love your fate and you
know that's that's the whole thing right
you just accept it right 2008 Jiraiya
thought that he was the first to
discover it but then his answer to that
question was the wrong answer and that's
why he went mad that's that's directs
Terry about Nietzsche which is the
fascinating theory because had he
answered no so here's the question now
all boils down to this do we or don't we
sacrifice had Nietzsche said the answer
that question is no then Nietzsche would
have had to be would have in order to
explain the answer he would have had to
turn around and find the cultural
sources of that answer and he may have
found himself dead smack in the middle
of the Bible recognizing that that is
the actual source of the answer that
question and then he may have changed
his mind on some of his some of his kind
of nations of Christianity or at least
he would have returned to a new critique
of Christianity not that he would have
rejected what he had already said about
Christianity but that he would have had
a new something new to say about not
only Christianity but the Judaism as
well in other words it would have
recognized more deeply the Bible sure I
thought this was I mean I don't know if
tried said that I sort of I inferred
that from Jiraiya I think anyway to make
it long story short we are our culture
is rooted every all human culture comes
from one linguistic nugget after another
compiled and just forgotten and
composted in toward the underbelly of
the human mental experience which is all
each and every one of them is a is an
entity of hypocrisy
and and the only way we know this is
because the Bible has shown it to us it
then this is why this is the reason why
the Bible is important because it's draw
points out that it says it explicitly
and yet it took us 2,000 years to figure
it out even though when we figure it out
it's completely explicit and obvious
it's like how come we couldn't figure it
out sooner why why didn't we
why didn't we figure this out a hundred
years after the but the Christian
Testament was what the Gospels were
written you know why wasn't why wasn't
it common knowledge in 200 AD instead of
1972 or whatever you mean the common
knowledge and the message being no
saying no no to sacrifice so yes and the
answer for Gerard is it was so deeply
unconscious that even though the met the
the wording and the message was
completely explicit and completely
obvious it was so deeply unconscious in
us that we didn't have the capacity to
learn it took us took us 2,000 years to
to to absorb the the information
together that what mod modernity is then
is that modernity is in a sense denying
this this whole notion of sacrifice I
mean it's not there yet but it's it's at
least I mean I I don't want to go into
that right away because my answer that
is no but I that would take a lot of
time to explain the but he and and
here's the here's the big argument this
is why I Gerard as a Christian and and
anyy believes in God me the this has to
be an intervention there it has to be a
force which we dumb we just it took us
two thousand years to figure out what is
in what was in fact they very explicitly
explained and and and in a simple
language and and what when you figure it
out is totally obvious but yes it is
it's it took us 2,000 years to process
it now they said so he's talking about
the two thousand year difference in time
is is
Gerard's argument that we have to pay
attention to this we it's he points out
that it is explicit
it's simply written it is it doesn't
doesn't hide anything it just says it
straight it shows in in full
illustration through the through the
story of the trial and execution of
Jesus that that this is this is the way
we came to be our human culture came to
be and yet and yet it took us two
thousand years to figure it out even
though it's totally explicit so what
about other cultures like that's true
but there's other cultures that were
evolved at the same time as he says
there are no exception to this
particular pagan phenomenon of yes
that's where I object that's where
there's this a triumphalism that I feel
that is is not like you know what is the
Buddha discover you know and what did
you know what did other cultures
discover where did the Chinese discover
the Taoist discover one you know I
totally agree with those objections and
they're very important objections but
they don't delve into the question of
human sacrifice but they obviously had
there were other avenues of the
improvement of the human condition and
and arguably full-on spiritualization of
humans that's that's I don't have any
issue with that but there were different
avenues the dealing with dealing with
the issue of human sacrifices is is one
which is the great distinction of the
judeo-christian cultural vein and much
much much greater than any other culture
not that the other cultures don't have I
mean I'm a very indebted feel very
indebted to Western philosophy for
example to idealism to European idealism
but European idealism is not this this
is very this is different this is a the
Jewish the biblical tradition is not the
idealist tradition to biblical tradition
delves deep down into the darkest the
darkest recess of the human cultural
mind in order to contain in order to
control and contain something and so
that we we we don't let this dark force
controller so over and over again and
what it's basically the continuing
medicine cycle of murder and peace and
war and peace just that just goes on and
on and on we can actually break that
cycle that's what the Bible is basically
saying I'm not saying that meditation
and yoga and all these other wonderful
traditions aren't they're different
they're doing different things but
they're not at they're not facing
head-on this this this problem of
collective murder but then why is this
why why does this happen in churches
over and over again you know like
pedophilia in the Catholic Church I'm
thinking oh why it seems they'll be the
same subject it's like hypocrisy and and
covering up the lion and this this this
sort of moralism on the surface and then
below the surface there's some sort of
human sacrifice going on yeah that's a
good question the sexuality is one of
the most momentous eyes subjects Manou
food sexuality sexuality because it's so
it's so exciting and it's so attached to
desire it
it is this subject that has had the most
the most mimetic concentration around it
so in other words it is the subject that
has led to the most collected murders in
in the past and that's that's and that's
why it's totally charged the search for
innocence is is basically here's here's
here's this is my most general
presentation of the Bible the Bible a
inhabits a larger metaphor which is a
trial and we're on trial and God is the
judge and the question is the simple
question is this this is the trial are
we innocent or are we guilty and that to
me is the the best way well the best way
for me in any case to frame the Bible is
to see it in that very strong basic
moral question are we innocent or are we
guilty now of course the answer that
question is always contextual
it's always get in every single context
in which we which were in and we can
identify I think with every decision we
make we can identify innocence and guilt
and this becomes this becomes this very
difficult process and we look at all the
details and we we still identify
identify at least every in many
decisions I make identify guilt identify
that there's a degree of wrongness and
thus is degree of rightness well maybe
it may be a ignorant and or ignorance
and understanding whether oh yeah I know
I totally agree with you that this is a
process of learning absolutely we're
digging it up from the unconscious but
the Bible at least Gerard's Bible says
that we are that that the the the main
source of our guilt is the deflecting of
onto a scapegoat and and how it
basically has created a totally
delusional sense of reality that's such
an important idea isn't it so yeah yeah
basically all of our language all of our
language is ultimately illusioned now we
are engaged in a process of of sorting
it out so that it becomes progressively
less illusory and and I would you ask me
about modernity I would say modernity is
part and parcel of that process this the
drought I would not come Gerrard is not
a modern thinker he's he is what people
he he I think he calls himself a non
structuralist thinker and non
structuralism is for me the proper name
for what I think is a misnomer which is
what people most people call
post-modernism in my opinion in my
opinion anybody uses the term
post-modernism or post structuralism it
doesn't understand what they mean
it means it's a it's an immediate
indication that they don't understand
it's not structuralism means that
there's a principle which permeates
every single every single category and
every single joinery of structure and
it's the same principle so there's a
principle of sameness Girard has a lot
to say about sameness and so it's
there's this same there's in may there
may not be just one Prince well there
might be many principals but all in all
the the many nurses own is a corollary
of the one principle which is related to
this whole issue of scapegoating and the
negation of scapegoating we history is
the process of or at least
judeo-christian history is the process
of turning that on its head and and and
defending the falsely accused the fuck
when we do that to defend the falsely
accused is to look at this subjectivity
this this great infinitely complex array
of objectivity that's before us and to
understand that most of it as false
accusation everything that we see our
entire understanding of the world when
we look at the sky when we talk about
the Stars and the planets and the Sun
and thought about people we talk about
history so illusion or Maya or something
yeah it's all based on just layers and
layers of false accusation and and false
peace
related and false data 5-piece related
to what you know the whole the whole
cycle of this what he calls the
scapegoat mechanism and anyway so when
we think that and we become very
skeptical of our sense of objectivity we
become extremely skeptical of it and we
begin to but we also recognize that we
have no choice but to sift through it
very very slowly knowing even if we
sniff through slowly we're probably
gonna get it wrong and so this becomes
this whole other thing and we it's not
that we're and the to be a Jewish
believer or a Christian believer in
other words to be a Jewish theist or a
Christian theist is to understand that
divine intervention is engaged in this
process of dismantling the false
accusation and the false peace wife
because the word because the word of the
Bible the Word of God is is is the only
tool we have which gave us the ability
to understand this that's why it's the
tool which gave us the the understanding
of this which revealed the scapegoat
mechanism and then allowed us to have
the
ability to to to defend the innocent
victim which is the absolute and the
innocent victim is not just some person
who's alive who's in your life but you
know some interpretation of the sky well
that whole interpretation of the skies
is totally wrong
you know I was talking talking about
your suit of truth in a sense yes well
I'm extrapolating that I'm taking a leap
from you know defending the witch being
burned on the stake to to truth claims
when you start to analyze truth claims
you start to recognize that there's a
whole bunch of file sizes false
accusations and pointing finger pointing
going around something you know
such as you know eggs eggs will cause
your heart to to you if you eat too many
eggs you you'll collect you get a bad
cholesterol that's a that these days is
is thought to be a false accusation
basically a false theory is basically
you know get eggs were put on trial and
they were found to be guilty oh that's
interesting is more health you see and
so now we and sorting so maybe it's this
this human desire to fabricate something
right it's so powerful in us to eat
maybe it's a lie they make this intense
lie about everything right or to believe
in concretize something into some truth
that's and you're not yet you haven't
yet really extend of it you know you
know I mean absolutely like it's it's a
hasty truth you've you've got there too
early yeah exactly and everybody not
only that the whole collective side they
collected murder side everybody jumps on
board everybody believes that eggs are
bad for your heart you know everybody
and then okay and you know there's
that's the only one example there you
know there's all kinds of examples of
this now and I'm bringing out science to
say that we're still hi Lima Metis eyes
and draw brings up this point we are
still extremely maminta size although
we're way better than we used to be
and we still got a ways to go and that's
what we're not burning which is most of
the time
you know well Gerard's most favorite I
believe one day when when he's fine he
discovered it's amazing how late it sits
he should be he should be I mean should
be world-famous it's just and I think
the reason why is warframe is not is
because he's he was a biblical thinker
in a time and it wasn't cool to be
biblical that's it's kind of it's it's
it's sad and pathetic and and and the
reason for this in Giraud was angry
about this is because we are so a meta
sized mimetic we were meta sized to
shown biblical scholarship in the mid
20th century it was considered not to be
intelligent so we are our whole sense of
intellectual culture he points out is
extremely Metis eyes it doesn't it
doesn't get doesn't it's not looking at
all it's not looking in the right places
because it's too busy making false
accusations off or off over in some some
other corner of whatever you know
instead of actually you know identifying
the obvious problem and so this happens
all the time
the next stage of this would be
explaining you know the negative side of
victimology it's like gone the other way
right yeah people are people are
starting to think that people are taking
that on as they are the innocent victim
you know to extreme extense right yeah
well just before you know and I I
thought I thought of one before I talk
about that I thought about what I wanted
to say Jerrod had made this statement
which I believe one day will be a very
famous statement you know there are a
famous statements in intellectual
history I think therefore I am you know
there's a few others I can't think of a
few we've had yeah god is dead you know
and also in literature you know to be
you or not to be that was the question
there's there's there's a few really
famous phrases that they're not going
anywhere and Gerard said this he said we
did not stop burning witches because
science was invented rather science was
invented because we stopped burning the
witches
mmm-hmm to me that he just nails it with
that one totally nails it and he he
identifies he there's this great sense
in in Western intellectual history that
we were mired in the delusions the
stupid delusions of religion and then
Along Came science and showed us how
delusional religion was and now we are
sort of her minds are clarifying and
things were getting better and you know
the light what happened and thank God
we're out of that mire irreligious whole
and dresses you foolish foolish dummies
that's not that's not at all what
happened what happened was we were it
took us friggin fifteen hundred years to
or fourteen hundred years to recognize
that burning witches was was bad and
this is here's an interesting take on
witch burnings of the Middle Ages witch
burnings happen in the Middle Ages and
we look at witch burnings as being a
regrettable as a dark period of Western
European history because we were burning
witches for compounder years or
something like that here's what really
happened and it did happen and it wasn't
it was something dark and terrible but
that's not what happened we we were
doing something similar to that all
along we were there was there were you
know in the time of Jesus there were
crucifixions that was very common there
are other forms of lynchings go
happening right up through the Dark Ages
but what happened with them burning with
the witch burnings and I didn't bring
this up I didn't stress this enough when
I talked about collective murder the
trial the condemnation of the accused
person is always unanimous in the trial
going back in prehistory you know with
the witch burnings there were people in
the crowd who disagreed with what was
happening uh-huh and that I'm that
didn't happen before that did not happen
before it was unanimous that's why it
isn't in Israel I was wondering about
the guillotines because I know it in
Paris there you know people would line
up to watch this stuff it was a show you
know and that's not that's it 1789
Mnet's yeah it is amazing how late Holly
we are people are just just there was
just you know they had
had to the neighbors were complaining
because there were so many so many
guillotines going along it's a bit noisy
but and then the crowds were all getting
you know it would come out and watch
this and it would be you know Sunday
entertainment or yeah it's just crazy
just nothing
yeah that's it's just it's really
disturbing you think about it but the we
know that that was wrong and I think the
reason why we know that that was wrong
is because there were people in the in
the at the event who knew it was wrong
well what they're always people that
would would know something like that
would be wrong I mean no going back in
time no going back in time Giraud makes
the points that the the the guilty
verdict was unanimous and the the
movement away from the unanimity of the
guilty verdict it was very slow and his
act required required nothing less than
divine intervention is that because
people were just one collective mind
they hadn't individuated yet they hadn't
become that would be one way think from
themselves or or definition of
individuation yeah this is one source of
individuation for sure i agree i would
think i mean but the whole idealism what
the greeks get on with there seems to be
i think i think well this week we get it
gets murkier here now this could be my
argument gets really difficult here now
but you know nietzsche talks about this
master and slave morality sites or I
think Nietzsche's really important
it's funny when when I whenever I heard
people talking about Nietzsche I never
hear them talk much about the slave and
master masters that to me is Nietzsche's
great they talk about all kinds of other
stuff he's talked about I don't know the
will to power or something the the
master and slave his recognition of the
master and slave and how they evolved
and how we're at a period of history
where they're coming together that's
that would that was Nietzsche's great
theory that the Masters they've evolved
as separate culture separate morality
separate culture separate long each
other as distinct from each other and
this went on for a very long time and
this is basically prehistory developing
this and then
basically as presciently in the top I'm
of Nietzsche they were coming together
and and this was a problem this
Nietzsche saw Nietzsche saw many
problems with this and but also
recognized that that's what that's what
was going on that seems to me
Nietzsche's that seems to me is great
theoretical import all the other stuff
he's talking about is extraneous to that
particular insight well it's part of the
same insight as God is dead isn't it I
mean it yeah there's nobody above you
and nobody you know anymore it's like
people are leveling out so so we don't
think of we don't think of human beings
as having a higher their being higher
human beings than other human beings you
know they're just richer or poorer yeah
yeah yeah something like that yeah yeah
anyway why didn't I think of me shit
oh yes so the master and the slave I
think the Plato and Aristotle they and
ancient Greek philosophy an ancient
Greek culture period what has survived
to to to enrich us is derivative of
master culture and so they were
articulating a and they were clarifying
and working on and making and basically
master language which was derivative of
master culture and they were creating
philosophy out of that in a sense of
reality and view of the universe and all
of that all through the eyes of master
culture while Judaism is right down in
the muck of slave culture and
articulating it still has a master
dimension but it's it's it's it's
working on this scapegoat thing this is
working on this deep dark origin of
culture which and it's deeply rooted in
what was about freeing the people isn't
it and funny and it's but it's really
wrote it right down in the it's right
down in the bottom of the right in the
bedrock of culture well you know there's
something about the Greeks which is this
you know they're up in the sky there's
their gods you know they're there did
their different different altogether
there so that's a really interesting
thing about
the Jewish important what I'm really
talking about here is Judaism although
and you're talking about it through the
eyes of the Gospels through the lens of
the Gospels mm-hmm
I've recently kind of developed an
elaborate theory of anti-semitism which
I'm kind of proud of but I'm going to
cut right down to the simple part about
that yeah it's well maybe I won't
simplify let's go through it very
quickly
Thomas draw Sol talks about the
middleman we we've come to see Jews as
associated with money and and and and
and all things all things you know good
and bad about money
the this is a latter-day cultural
development and I think it's a result of
the deprivation of private property that
the back because of Christian
persecution not that I know I'm not much
of an historian but basically what they
develop was that culture the middle man
now the middle man has to put in Thomas
All Souls words is it very badly
misunderstood figure it the middle
manner basically is essential to
economics so they they buy their
basically buy and sell and if there's no
if there's nobody out there buying and
selling then you don't have a you don't
have a very functional economic economy
so these people are necessary and so and
the middleman it's very common for the
middleman and I mean you know in many
cultures to be resented and to be blamed
and to be thought that they're being
whoever whoever the middleman is just
cheating them of something and maybe at
times they are maybe maybe at other
times they're not but the truth is
they're necessary so whether we like it
or not they're there they're there
they're there now competition between
middlemen and brings down the dishonesty
you get a much better deal in this
competition like in Newfoundland we had
what we call the merchants economy here
and merchants who this theory developed
nah I'm starting to realize it's a
result of the onslaught of Marxist
culture into into Western economic
theory where we recognize the merchants
these terrible people who cheated out
the the fisherfolk of Newfoundland and I
think we might want to have a second
look at that history I think that might
be a very skewed not that it's not that
there isn't some truth to it but I like
I've been thinking about the
Newfoundland folk songs and there's not
a lot there's not a lot of Newfoundland
folk songs which hates the merchants it
seems like it's a relatively recent in
introduction we were taught by theory it
seems to hate the merchants well it
seems at one time we it was understood
to be a just a necessary part of life it
was it was it was a piece of the puzzle
right a piece of the larger fabric and
that you know without which she could
not survive kind of thing a bit like a
king you know a king a king is both
worshipped and reviled depending on the
king depending on the cultures something
like that the so anyway middleman and
middleman cultures are often persecuted
and often reviled the Armenians were
middlemen for example they they suffered
persecution the year there were other
middlemen in in Eastern Africa Thomas
all talks about there's another
middleman culture he mentions forget now
well basically there are several
cultures which are middlemen cultures
which which end up being persecuted and
being suspected of you know cheating so
it's a common thing and yet the
middleman is is is a necessary piece of
the puzzle so you're damned if you do
and you're damned if you don't kind of
thing yeah so so that's that's what I
think this is the most this is an
important reason for anti-semitism but
it's escaped scapegoat again and going
back yeah yeah that's right that's the
only beginning the second reason is I
think far more important than the first
and there there's I right I I'm thinking
in terms of three reasons the third
reason is the most important the second
reason has to do with the fall of Roma
what happened was Rome fell and
basically Europe became overrun by what
would I call for for both for
provocation but also of seriousness the
Catholic Taliban the Catholic Taliban
basically took over
all of Europe correct position right
that's the no no you're talking the dark
ages Inquisition something else yeah
dark ages
dark ages was a time of and a lot of
people don't know this this is something
I only learned recently shortly after
the fall of Rome the Muslim world
attacked and advanced and took much of
Christendom from from Christendom
Christendom had extend it down into down
into the Middle East and was a you know
it was fairly large and and then the
Muslim world began to infringe upon
Christendom and it took over vast
amounts of territory and this went on
this this advancement continued for four
hundred years I couldn't believe it
yes I didn't know this but basically the
entire Dark Ages is characterized by war
with the Muslim world and the Muslim
world was the aggressor and the the
Europe Catholic Europe was basically a a
it seems to me and basically a place
which forever was reeling from the fall
of her own in other words it was some
civilizational place and because it was
cut cut off from the power of her own
sort of thing it had been isolated or
well it basically didn't have a
civilization to hold it together it was
no longer civilization it seemed
disparate I don't know I don't know what
it was it seems but but if in some
strange way it remained a Catholic
entity like a Christian entity and when
despite the fact that for 400 years it
was a war with Islam essentially and at
a certain about 400 years later 900 or
something they they finally started to
push back the Muslim world I don't know
if the Crusades have anything Crusades
were later couple centuries later I
don't know if they're related but I mean
some people think of it as blowback but
I don't know anyway well back to the
here's the thing all the
catholic Taliban yeah yeah here's the
thing so the Catholic Europe is at war
has basically imposed a christened 'm
over europe it's at war with with the
muslim world but the jews aren't
Christians and not only that this this
Europe at the time is a theocracy it is
there there is no separation of state
religion it is it is religion that
reigns and this is another theory I've
derived from thinking about this is that
when you know religion is a sub level is
the self is a level below secularity
it's a level below the the empty
imperial realm so when the Empire Falls
when civilization Falls what you have is
religion and that's not a certain could
take I mean I'm a defender of religion
but a religion without the the upper
level that's that's that's kind of it's
basically the Taliban it's it's a it's
something in other words some kind of
mixture of gangsterism and religion will
will reign over the land in the place
where civilization collapses and so
that's kinda that's my understanding of
what happened in the Dark Ages in Europe
however the Jews remained a distinct
group they would not pledge allegiance
to Christianity would not say that they
are Christians and what that amounts to
in a theocracy is treason it doesn't
just amount to heresy or some other form
of you really just it's it's not a
religious act to not pledge allegiance
to another religion in a theocracy it's
also an act of treason because you are
not in a sense pledging allegiance to
the governing force well it's kind of
like the Christians now in the Muslim
world maybe you know I mean I have some
more theocratic Muslim countries and the
Christians who are stuck there being
persecuted well this is why the
separation of state religion is so
important because in a Innis in a state
which is identical with
to not espouse that particular religion
istic is to is to not is to be against
the government of that land and that's
the governing force and that's that's uh
that's treason and they committed they
did that for 400 years now it's amazing
that they did that they they managed to
to swing that and and I'm and I'm sure
more that they did it for providential
reasons reasons you know they couldn't
give up their Jewish identity for for
deeper reasons they know the Jews are
survivors
yeah but nonetheless to to not see this
not understand this in that context is
treasonous and to knots and to see that
that this might not for a very long time
and to accuse Christianity of just
simply making a tree or something based
on this is not quite right because it is
quite possible that they could have been
allies with the Muslim invaders for
example it's more than possible because
they weren't friends into Christians if
you if you see it from that point it
from that perspective and so so they in
other words if you're not with us then
you may be with me you may well be with
them and that's that and let's not
forget it was it was four years of war
so I'm thinking that there's that this
is this is all right this may well be an
extremely important source of
anti-semitism which because I went out
for so long because of this very
entrenched in people's just totally
entrenched in me and you know
Catholicism still maintained sovereignty
until the modern age arrived until an HS
state sort of started to upend it so in
other words there was still this sense
of sorry you know there was that not
much separation between state and
religion until the modern times until
the nation-state but it doesn't go back
it doesn't it go back to Jesus and Paul
and and all of that I mean Paul no no I
haven't gotten there that's that's the
second cause so I just described the
here's another thing so I just talked
about sovereignty basically I just
talked about the the
the fusion of state and religion and
that means that religion is identical in
a theocracy with the sovereign state a
lot of people don't realize this
property is simply an attribute a it's a
subcategory of sovereignty when you
organize the territory the land the
Kingdom in terms of its property you're
mapping out all this property some of it
may be private property sure but you're
still mapping it out from us from the
perspective of sovereignty and not
suffer from a perspective of taxation
denying Jews property would have had to
do with sovereignty because after all
they were they were treasonous
ultimately treasonous if you see what I
mean that means they means they weren't
to be denied property is to mean your it
means you're not a full member of the
state that means soon I'm getting that
this is all a function of this this the
second reason I'm talking about this
denial of property and the entrenchment
of anti-semitism due to its relationship
to sovereignty to - to treason to the
fact that if you're not with us you're
against us in in this very difficult
time of maintaining the the sovereignty
of the land and of Christianity which
was identical with the state you know
getting it so that's this the denying
property where but when I want to go to
is it is the level deeper where Jacob
and Esau are at war even in the womb
right okay keeps talking about this this
like they were at war in the womb
already of Sarah well you said something
me already about lack of the Levites and
and I we agreed completely so here's the
third reason is by far the most
important reason the Jews had four
reasons I don't fully understand
developed a strong antipathy a strong
and it was they felt it was their divine
providence to oppose human sacrifice so
there was a deep commit
cultural commitment inside Judaism is
usually a part of their identity to
oppose human sacrifice it was a deep and
and so they and so they identify
themselves as anti paying and they were
did that was that's fundamental to their
identity is to not be and we are all
invited the the Gentiles into the church
right yeah that's right so so along
comes the the Gospels and what they do
is they portray a human sacrifice they
portray someone being executed and and
tried and executed miss tried and
executed for all the wrong reasons it's
a totally insane
trial and execution the Jews look at
that and they say that is a human
sacrifice we got nothing to do with that
that's pagan shit man we're not going
anywhere we're not going anywhere near
it that's not that's not Jewish when in
fact what that was is it was indeed a
human sacrifice it was a deed it was
indeed a journey right down into the
heart of the pagan the pagan mindset and
yet it went down in it it penetrated
right into the heart of the pagan
mindset with Jewish cultural insight
with Jewish cultural importance so it
was in fact Jewish all of the insights
which show that that this is wrong that
this is this has to be dismantled came
was information that was already
contained in the Jewish testament right
and and of course Jew Jesus was a Jewish
rabbi now that that's who so in other
words but so what happened and in fact
the the fact that this great Jewish
insight penetrated right down into the
heart of paganism that is what made this
particular portrayal of a collective
murder of human sacrifice the most
powerful story that is ever written
about a human sacrifice about a
collective murder
that the power of that story is what
attracted the pagan audience in much
greater numbers than ever before there
had been numerous stories about
sacrifices right it's just that they
weren't it weren't worth shit they would
win DeLand die their work because every
word they were they were Donna doesn't
in fact and but this one had all in a
crazy amount of power and the reason was
because of the Jewish imports that made
that gave it all the power and the power
was to dismantle it in fact to negate it
the pagans audience was so magnetically
drawn to this and that's your exterior
right it's the sense nice to end
sacrifice exactly yeah exactly yeah he
he's actually more he's more careful
about that he's much more this is why I
think of him as a Jewish thinker he
doesn't say it's the sacrifice to wind
I'll second verse even though that's a
very interpretation to make and that's
the that's the common Christian I think
that would probably be more a more
traditional Catholic argument the
sacrifice to end all sacrifices but he
says no no no it's a it was actually
just a mistrial it's actually just wrong
so he he's kind of Jewish in that he
goes right down there with this Jewish
insight and says it's actually just a
bunch of bullshit and but yet it was a
divine intervention to really reveal it
at all the bullshit so he doesn't like
the preordained sacrificial mission of
Jesus to go down there and be killed he
knew it was gonna happen yeah straight
away from that he doesn't like it he
thinks that lends itself to sacrificial
he one of his biggest ideas was that
religion needed to be desacralized
and Christianity particularly needed to
be T sacralized he I think changed his
mind at the very end of his life oh yeah
I want to object to that but but he
changed his mind at the very end of his
life he had a funny he had a he had a an
insight at the very end in the last few
years it's in the his interview in the
idea of with David Cayley he says only
very recently he said have I learned
this have I discovered this that
sacrifice has two meanings so he
he had basically devoted his entire
intellectual career to one particular
meaning of sacrifice which basically is
the type of sacrifice which is horrific
and needed to be negated to be stopped
and then the other kind is the kind of
jordan Peterson talks about maybe
there's another kind and giving up or
the future or it's much it's complex and
I think it has to do my taking on it I I
never I never journeyed into what Tehran
had to say about I'm not sure he had
said much to say about it he was kind of
poor he's gone by then I think but but
my take is just it just synonymous with
existentialism every with every decision
you make you are missing a million you
know an infinite number of other
decisions you know I'm drinking a glass
of water here which means I'm not
drinking orange juice or whatever means
I'm I'm not you know holy I'm holding
this glass instead of holding my phone I
mean um every with every just every even
the tiniest decisions made you are
omitting every other decision that can
be possibly made I'm chatting with you
while I could be out you know you know
could be a scoring babes yeah exactly I
was gonna say something more vulgar but
you got a you said the same thing you
anticipated so yeah so that's what I but
I don't know that's one definition of
the positive distance in other words
that's we we are daily or mid upon
minute life is is fundamentally
sacrificial yeah but there's a whole
other aware this this impulse to blame
he's he sees that we absolutely have to
extricate in that's good that's good
that we're separating those two
definitions they absolutely have to
extricate blame and and leave it and
contain it all for him to blame he
basically I think he thinks that all
forms of blame her there's basically
ultimately no I think I think he it's a
it's a radical it's a he's he's he's
radically moving us towards a blameless
although I mean it's hard to say like he
thinks
example Nietzsche in many ways wasn't
was a the Godfather of Nazism he says
that in that essay about in the in his
final book which is pretty strong thing
to say and that's kind of like a blame
so so maybe maybe he maybe he's maybe he
does reserve some blame I don't know
and where was I oh yes so the the only
reason the story of the crucifixion the
Christian passion is so enormously
powerful is because of the is the
insertion of Jewish anti sacrificial
Jewish desacralized power right down
into the right down into the the core
recurrent recurring identity of paganism
which is you know sacrificed a
collective murder the pagans look at
this and they're totally drawn to it
because first of all they're drawn to
collect a murder anyway they're drawn to
human sacrifice that's their natural
religious night magnetic draw and then
they are witnessing all this information
that they'd never heard before they
never saw before and it's just it's just
this explosion of this massive learning
curve right for the pagans but but the
problem with that is is it momenta sized
it at the same time what happens is
pagan culture which was would have been
like a big ocean surrounding the Jewish
identity floods completely floods and
inundates
the the Christian passion story and then
owns it as its own and so Christian the
real Brit
after a very short time the birth of
Christianity is ultimately Jewish and
very very shortly after that thereafter
it is it is something else lost it is
owned by a pagan identity and what
happens is the the Jewish the Jewish
seed only very very slowly grows inside
that thing what happens is is Rome you
know Imperial Rome you know but I mean
Christianity was only adopted as as the
official religion late in Rome I don't
know what was before but yeah it slowly
it's not I'm not really speaking right
now yeah I yeah yeah and so that's that
but here's the thing the pagan flood
combined with the Jewish
the flood of that and an embracement of
that the Christian passion combined with
the the Jewish reaction and and we being
repelled from the Christian passion on
the grounds that it is it is human
sacrifice one is repelled one rejects it
the other embraces it and yet it is
fundamentally Jewish so there's this
totally bizarre contradiction at work
they read and and so what happens is
this pagan flood adopts this totally
Jewish identity very close to the Jewish
identity when you have two Jewish
identity we rejects it there right there
yeah this is the great these are way
greater numbers than the Jewish identity
the reactive reactionary Jew mmm-hmm and
they're so it's a it's right at the
birthplace in many ways of Christianity
that anti-semitism is born and and
that's both a what I was talking about
the you know had a beautiful thing to
hear Jews being that they're
representing the idea of the
nation-state right the the State of
Israel though and you know Christianity
has a kind of universal theme and
Judaism as it has a theme of of
nationalism or something our nation
that's not that's me I prepare phrasing
or or yeah yeah yeah yeah sure if I've
got that right I heard I heard bird talk
a little bit about that it's true that
there's a universalism in Christianity I
I would back away I mean there's a whole
there's a whole ultra-conservative not
all what do they call them
ultra-orthodox Jewish people who think
that nationhood in Judaism contradictory
to each other and that's my
understanding of Judaism as well and so
there's something about and the reason
is Judaism the nation is ultimately
synonymous with the tribal identity and
the nation-state and the tribal I didn't
get into this with your rapid tribal
identity is a product of
of pockets of culture which are created
through cycles of momentous ISM in the
skate and scapegoating the collective
murder which create greets the state but
the nation is bigger than the tribe it's
it's a collection of tribes you know
under the nation-state eventually
emerged institutionally much later I was
only it was only a few years old right
the the I think my understanding of the
nation-state is that it is fundamentally
sacrificial in in the negative sense it
grew out of it grew out of grew out of
murder even though they're they're a
positive ideals that work to the the
it's my feeling is that Israel is an
imitation of the Christian creation of
the nation-state in other words England
France these these other all these
European countries and small wants to
they that that Israel we imitate it
there and and that really Israel in my
view my view about Israel is that I
don't take Zionism very seriously
I don't think Zionism is is seriously
central to Israel although it has become
increasingly so I think the Holocaust is
far and away the most identifying force
the most important force that that is
that is fueled Israeli identity in other
words in my in I think the word Israel
is almost a synonym of never again
that's how I think of Israel and the
reason for the leave the the intensity
around Israeli identity is it's
certainly not clear that it there it
that it will it will be never again and
at least in my view there still is
teeming under the under the surface of
Western identity anti-semitism
oh yeah that's coming up it seems to be
it's yeah it's really it's a strange
thing I find it very strange yeah if I
see you get little hits of anti-semitism
here and there you know you did somebody
said something on Facebook or it's like
you feel it kind of bubbling to the
surface all over again you know I think
if you understand Gerard's theory
completely it becomes obvious why
there and the and you know I think
Jewish culture because of its deep
sensitivity to this scapegoat thing is
it has a Christianity as the term and de
semitism is a watered down version of
what it really is which is you know
rabbi Jacob would say you hate right you
know hate oh yeah how do we see
anti-semitism as if it's why don't we
just say hatred of Jews that would make
it more sure more direct no yes being
what it is right yeah I think we would
know what it is rather than this thing
oh what's anti-semitism yeah yeah no I
agree yeah I mean the Semites I mean
need the Arabs are Semites right so this
is kind of a strange strange word to be
used in assembly
anyway the some what I was going to say
the Israel will lose its its its sense
of urgent identity will diminish only
when it has confidence that that
anti-jewish sentiment is is something
that has been contained or has been
properly contained and and it hasn't
been and so the and so that is the
reason why I've often thought why why
couldn't they figure out the fucking
Palestine prep because Palestine
actually my understanding is they have a
fairly reasonable request
they had they've said that they have
their traditional land and it's only a
tani it's only a small part of Israel
it's the Gaza Strip in the West Bank and
and why can't why and this was back in
the PLO days with yes or ephra and so
that was Adam in the end and so if you
just give us the West Bank in the Gaza
and we leave you it alone we will you
know we can have two countries and and I
thought that myself why don't they
fucking agree to that and and after all
Israel's a tiny place anyway well it's
all in many ways just a symbolic it's a
symbolic center of Jewish culture it's
too small for a lot of them to live
there
but and but the answer is what I just
gave the answer
reason why they're there were it will
never really be fully resolved and that
they there's this sense of large
territory there and stuff is because of
is because never again is not a gay it's
not a given it's absolutely not a given
and the more the more the West falls
into turmoil the more you will have the
tendency to for French Semitism arise
when Asia explains it is that very
dismantling of the of the nagas that
that that that that deep dark not which
which is the the of him of human
hypocrisy which which keeps us mired in
in in in an endless cycle of illusion so
what you look at anything and you and
you look at any thought any feeling
that's in your mind and you look at any
theory out there any ideology and you
say to yourself is this is this in the
business of victimizing and and then you
analyze it and and and what you're in
what you're engaged in is this this
process of Absolution basically is there
a proper verb and unveiling layer upon
layer of illusion until until you could
get it not something more true you know
and usually the process I love the word
absolution because I think the
absolution word the Catholic sacrament
of absolution means the bringing
together understanding and forgiveness
the the word to be absolved mosz those
two things understanding and forgiveness
so we did the whole process of of
defending me innocent victim is really a
it's a gentle and but firm process
gentle and strong but it doesn't accuse
it's it's not in the business of
accusing and because it recognizes that
you just count up and you're caught up
in the usual sign up in the game if
you're accusing if you're on in a state
of accusing you're you're caught up in
the same old game you haven't been
gotten out of the
the trap that's right and he did warm he
saw it in his last book as an icy Satan
fall like lightning which by the way is
a quote from the Gospels he he he saw
the rise and what he called victimology
and he he knew that this was an
absolutely wretched development it's
hard it's hard to articulate remember
how what he said about it exactly but I
only only this week I thought of how
torture first of all when you're you're
embellishing your own victim egde
there's a usually an accusation engaged
in that you're accusing someone else and
they usually the accusation is false
that's part of it but another another
part is to to bring on too much
attention to a certain form of victim
inch which might which may indeed be
legitimate is possibly to obscure a much
greater victimization of another so
you're over stating if you're
overstating a certain victimization then
you are obscuring other more important
victimization more importantly what it
really I find it deeply tragic that
Renee's around is not more well-known
because there seems to be a gravitation
we're getting closer and closer to
understanding his very point the whole
point of scapegoating and the whole
point of victimizing but we're not there
and so when the closer you get to it the
more intense the feelings become because
it actually is this deep knot of
medicine that was about to unrest it's
hard to lay down your you know your
sword or yes exactly whatever it happens
to be right like you can feel we're
getting closer to this deep source of
terrible cultural origin which is deeply
proud of deeply very much a part of us
and it is fundamentally violent and it
is laden laden with mimetic intensity
just so everybody is in this hurry to
imitate and to belong and at the same
time they're aware that something's
gonna blow and and who's gonna be the
victim kinda who's gonna be the skate
who this is and it's and at the same
time it seems to me we're getting damn
close to just just man doing it and the
word I love the word out solution
there's something about it it's the
combination of of understanding in
forgiveness
so when you get a sense of whenever
people are start I mean I I found my
I've been getting him I get it's very
easy to get wrapped up into it it's
almost it in many ways it's almost
impossible because it's so fundamental
to us to not be menaced we fall victim
to it all the time and when a juror was
fairly aware of that that he he he
himself was subject to medicine he knew
that he quite possibly could be saying
mimetic things and you know pointing the
finger in way you know making false
accusation she was very aware of that it
was kind of fascinating to watch and be
so careful and and so aware of the the
possibility for sinned it's kind of yeah
it's a it's an amazing amazing theory
that's another I guess it could be a
definition of sin too right oh my god
yes you just say you just mentioned the
word sin so I thought yeah that what
that's what sin is is it's being
untruthful right it's missing the
markets yeah yeah absolutely it's you
know pointing fingers at innocent people
and you know to to avoid your own
existential business yeah yeah
absolutely absolutely and take the log
out of your own UI before you take
before you take splinter out of another
the be I've been thinking a lot about
sin this past couple weeks in it's like
there's the the extremely famous line of
Jesus on the cross forgive them Lord for
they know not what they do
Gerard proposes that this is in fact the
very first mention of the unconscious
this is this has no precedent he thinks
the the he may he may be wrong but he
suggests that in that the very first
mention of the unconscious is right
there forgiving them Lord for they know
not what they do the the problem with
not knowing what you do is it's hard to
call it sin if you know not what you do
but it seems to me that if when you know
what you do then it's sin yes so in
other words like if you're if you're
halfway knowing or mmm-hmm that's right
so this it seems to me we are engaged in
a progressive we are engaged in a
progression towards sin in other words
sin is a very enlightened term because
we are becoming a weak we are becoming
progressively aware of it now I know it
can be it can be corrupted I mean the
proud of the 20th century like Nietzsche
said we'd be more sinful II he wrote the
you know he was being ironic he was he
was he was he was taking his shot at the
moat Christian more of the shallow
morality right so obviously there are
humps in the ladder but nonetheless to
be I think this word sin is this
marvelous act march towards freedom in
fact because the more and more you are
aware of sin the more free aware and and
and the more even way even if you sin if
you become you're free because you are
aware that you are sinning or or or to
be to be aware of sin is also to be more
capable of avoiding it so that's that's
a good thing to of course that's the
best thing but if you sin and know
you're sitting you're still you're
exercising freedom you're aware of your
freedom so this is it's a march toward
freedom as well it's a kind of a
fascinating thing whereas back in in the
in in the time of the crucifixion of
Jesus arguably this doesn't count as sin
this is kind of a fascinating what
doesn't sound kind of sin is because
there's no there's nobody doing it it's
just the collective yeah
momentum yeah yeah there you have it